<sect1 id="install" xreflabel="Installing WebMail ACS 4.0">
  <title>Installing WebMail ACS 4.0</title>

  <para>WebMail is an ACS solution to allow users to check their mail
    via a web browser.</para>

  <sect2 id="install-pre-installation-tasks" xreflabel="Pre-Installation Tasks">
    <title>Pre-Installation Tasks</title>

    <para>Here we are going to check and see which of the following items
      we need to download.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
	<para>You must have Oracle 8.1.6, Intermedia, and ACS 4.0.1 or higher
	  installed to use WebMail.  It is also recommended that you install the 
	  acs-reference and acs-lang packages in order to allow Webmail to handle 
	  servers and clients operating in different timezones (if you do not install 
	  this, Webmail will display all times using the timezone that Oracle is 
	  running in).  Please make sure that these items are properly installed 
	  before proceeding.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>We will check to see if qmail is running.</para>

	<programlisting>
$ ps -ef | grep qmail
   qmails     593     1  0 16:36 ?        00:00:00 qmail-send
   qmaill     604   593  0 16:36 ?        00:00:00 splogger qmail
   root       605   593  0 16:36 ?        00:00:00 qmail-lspawn ./Mailbox
   qmailr     606   593  0 16:36 ?        00:00:00 qmail-rspawn
   qmailq     607   593  0 16:36 ?        00:00:00 qmail-clean
   root      1256  1241  0 18:47 pts/0    00:00:00 grep qmail
$
	</programlisting>

	<simpara>This output means that qmail is installed and running. If you
	  have problems with your qmail install please consult 
	  <xref linkend="install-appendix-a-troubleshooting"></xref>
	  any further help can be found at 
	  <ulink url="http://www.qmail.org">www.qmail.org</ulink>.</simpara>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>We will check to see if java is installed.</para>

	<programlisting>
$ which jar
   /usr/local/java/bin/jar
$
	</programlisting>

	<para>You should have output similar to this meaning that you have java
	  installed. And that you have <emphasis>jar</emphasis> which is the 
	  needed utility.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-acquiring-needed-items" xreflabel="Acquiring Needed Items">
    <title>Acquiring Needed Items</title>

    <para>Everything you download here should be stored in the /tmp
      directory of your machine. This is not required but the rest of the
      document will reference the files as if they are in the temp
      directory. To complete this install, you will need access to a user in
      the dba group and root.</para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://www.qmail.org">Qmail</ulink>: Qmail is the mail
	  delivery tool we will use to send a recieve mail from your web
	  server. This should replace sendmail.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/jdk/1.2/download-linux.html">Java
	    Development SDK</ulink>: This is used for the jar utility. Generally
	  java is also a good idea to have installed on your system.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>To install the java portion of webmail you need to have the
	  JavaMail library from <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/">http://java.sun.com/products/javamail/</ulink>
	  and the JavaBeans Activation Framework from <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/beans/glasgow/jaf.html">http://java.sun.com/beans/glasgow/jaf.html</ulink>.</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-setting-up-qmail-very-important" xreflabel="Setting up Qmail (Very Important)">
    <title>Setting up Qmail (Very Important)</title>

    <para>The following are instructions to modify the qmail install to be
      compatible with WebMail. Qmail should already be installed and
      running for this step. If not, follow instructions from <ulink url="http://www.qmail.org">qmail.org</ulink> or ask your systems
      administrator. The instructions are for a default installation. If
      you need to modify the default settings, consult Appendix C. 
    </para>

    <para><phrase>There is a script to make this task easier.</phrase> However,
      this script was written on a Sun server and is not gauranteed to work 
      correctly on your particular flavor of UNIX.  You should review its 
      contents to verify that it will work properly for your particular 
      machine and configuration.  The script is at 
      <computeroutput>/webmail/scripts/wm-qmail-setup</computeroutput>.
      It must be run as root and automates all the steps outlined below in 
      this section.  After running the script, proceed to 
      <xref linkend="install-installing-the-package"></xref>.
    </para>

    <para>If you choose not to run the script, please follow the directions 
      below to configure qmail for Webmail.
    </para>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem><para>You must know what domain name you are going to use for your
	  email e.g. here.there.com. You must then add your domain name to
	  the <filename>rcpthosts</filename> file. This will tell qmail to accept mail for
	  your domain. This file might or might not exist. If it doesn't
	  exist create one. 

	  <phrase>Note that you should use the home directory of AOL Server if it
	    is not /home/aol32 wherever appropriate.</phrase>

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# cd /var/qmail/control
# vi rcpthosts; on a new line simply add your domain name:
here.there.com
# exit
$
	  </programlisting>

	</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Create an alias directory and make sure it can be written to by
	  the nsadmin user. 

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# mkdirhier /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias
# chown -R nsadmin:web /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Add the following line to /var/qmail/control/virtualdomains.
	  This file may or may not exist if it does not exist just create it.


	  <programlisting>
$ su
# cd /var/qmail/control
# vi virtualdomains; add a line like this:
here.there.com:webmail-there
# exit
$
	  </programlisting>

	  Now we will decompose the string: <computeroutput>here.there.com:webmail-there</computeroutput>

	  <orderedlist>
	    <listitem><para><computeroutput>here.there.com</computeroutput> : 
		This is the hostname that resolves to the
		webserver you are on. This is also the second half of your 
		email address 
		<computeroutput>*@here.there.com</computeroutput>.
	      </para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><computeroutput>webmail-there</computeroutput> : 
		This is prepended to the email address. So,
		mail sent to 
		<computeroutput>foo@here.there.com</computeroutput> will be 
		delivered internally by qmail as 
		<computeroutput>webmail-there-foo@here.there.com</computeroutput>.
		This is so we 
		can tell qmail to deliver the messages to Webmail instead of 
		to the usual maildirs in each users home directory. In this 
		case, the string "webmail" will be the qmail "account" which 
		handles the mail for qmail, and "there" will be an identifier 
		for Webmail associated with the 
		<computeroutput>here.there.com</computeroutput> domain.
	      </para></listitem>
	  </orderedlist>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Run the following to find the user id and the group id of
	  Oracle: 

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# su - oracle 
$ id
uid=101(oracle) gid=102(oinstall)
$ exit
# exit
$
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem>
	<para>
	  Insert a line into <filename>users/assign</filename>.
	  This file might or might not exist if it doesn't exist create one.

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# cd /var/qmail/users
# vi assign; add a line like this:
+webmail-:oracle:101:102:/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias:-::
.
# exit
$
	  </programlisting>

	  Make sure this file is ended by a line consisting of a single dot
	  (.).
	</para>

	<simpara>
	  Now we will decompose the string: 
	  <filename>+webmail-:oracle:101:102:/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias</filename>
	</simpara>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>+webmail-</computeroutput> : 
	      This is the name of the account that is going to
	      handle all of the mail that comes in for webmail. WebMail reads all
	      the mail as it comes into this account and figures out which user
	      it is meant for and forwards it on to them.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>oracle</computeroutput> :
	      This is the user that has permission to read the mail
	      and shove it into the database.</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>101</computeroutput> : This is the user id for oracle</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>102</computeroutput> : This is the group id for oinstall</para></listitem>

	  <listitem><para><computeroutput>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias</computeroutput>: This is
	      the alias directory which qmail will search when it delivers mail.
	      Webmail will insert user alias files here.</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

      </listitem>

      <listitem><para>Choose a queue directory for deliveries to the webmail user.
	  This directory must not be shared with any other virtual server
	  running on the same machine;
	  <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue</filename> should be a
	  safe choice. Create the directory and make sure it is writable and
	  readable by the oracle Unix account (or whatever user Oracle runs
	  at): 

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# /var/qmail/bin/maildirmake /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue
# chown -R oracle /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Now restart qmail. Run 

	  <programlisting>
# /var/qmail/bin/qmail-newu
# ps -ef | grep qmail
<replaceable>find the "qmail-send" PID</replaceable>
# kill -HUP <replaceable>qmail-send PID</replaceable>
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-installing-the-package" xreflabel="Installing the package">
    <title>Installing the package</title>

    <para>First, you will have to obtain a copy of the Webmail package.
      Then use the APM to install and enable the package. When given the
      option, <phrase>do not</phrase> install the 
      <filename>MessageParser.sqlj</filename> and
      <filename>MessageComposer.sqlj</filename> files. We will install these 
      by hand later.
      <phrase>Do</phrase> install the <filename>webmail-create.sql</filename> file though.</para>

    <para>Next you must create an instance of Webmail. Go to the site-map
      and make a new sub-folder under <filename>/</filename> called 
      <filename>webmail</filename> (you may choose a different mount point if you like). 
      Click <emphasis>new application</emphasis> under this new webmail folder
      and select the webmail package and give it a name. Then set the
      following parameters:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
	  AliasDirectory=/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias/</computeroutput></para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><computeroutput>
	  QueueDirectory=/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/</computeroutput></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You may also choose different names for the four default mailboxes 
      (INBOX, SENT, DRAFTS, and TRASH) if you prefer, by editing 
      the appropriate parameters.  The parameter ShowMailboxInfo should be 
      set to "t" if you want to display the number of unread/total messages
      in each mailbox on the side nav-bar ("f" if not; this is both a UI
      and a performance consideration).</para>

    <para>To allow for proper display of dates accross timezones, make sure you have
      installed the acs-lang package and set the system timezone to 
      the timezone which Oracle is running in.  The timezones of the clients 
      are individually set in the preferences section of the Webmail UI.</para>

    <para>After setting these parameters, restart your aolserver so they
      can be read in upon startup.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-loading-in-java-to-oracle" xreflabel="Loading in Java to Oracle">
    <title>Loading in Java to Oracle</title>

    <para>If you do not already have the JavaMail package and the JavaBeans
      Activation Framework already loaded into Oracle, you will have to
      do so now. </para>

    <para>There is a script to make this easier at <computeroutput>
      /webmail/scripts/wm-java-setup</computeroutput>.
      It should be run from the /tmp directory, and the zipped 
      JavaMail and JAF jar files should be placed in the /tmp 
      directory before running the script.  After the script has 
      completed succesfully, proceed to <xref linkend="install-testing-the-system"></xref>.
    </para>

    <para>Alternatively, you may do it by hand:</para>

    <para>This loads the JavaBeans Activation Framework:

      <programlisting>
$ cd /tmp
$ unzip jaf1_0_1.zip
$ unzip javamail1_1_3.zip
$ cd jaf-1.0.1
$ jar xvf activation.jar
$ rm activation.jar
$ jar cf0M activation.jar META-INF javax com
$ loadjava -user <replaceable>dbuser/dbuserpasswd</replaceable> -resolve -verbose activation.jar
      </programlisting>
    </para>
    
    <para>Don't worry if you get a verification warning, as long as there are
      no errors.</para>

    <programlisting>
This loads the JavaMail Program
$ cd ../javamail-1.1.3
$ jar xvf mail.jar       
  --(if you get a could not create directory error, just run the command again, it should go away)
$ rm mail.jar
$ jar cf0M mail.jar META-INF javax com
$ loadjava -user <replaceable>dbuser/dbuserpasswd</replaceable> -resolve -verbose mail.jar
    </programlisting>

    <para>Now we will go into the webmail directory and load the java
      packages associated with it.
    
    <programlisting>
$ cd /web/<replaceable>yourservicename</replaceable>/packages/webmail/java
$ loadjava -user <replaceable>dbuser/dbpasswd</replaceable> -resolve -verbose BlobDataSource.java ClobDataSource.java StringBufDataSource.java MessageParser.sqlj MessageComposer.sqlj
    </programlisting>

      The loader will probably complain about some errors. Don't worry about it 
      because they're actually just a bunch of warnings.  As long as the loader does not 
      say <computeroutput>ORA-29535: source requires recompilation</computeroutput> you are okay.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-testing-the-system" xreflabel="Testing the system">
    <title>Testing the system</title>

    <para>Now load up the page for <ulink url="/webmail/admin">webmail/admin</ulink>. Register your domain with
      the webmail system by using the administration pages, with (again,
      just for this example) "there" as the short name and
      "<computeroutput>here.there.com</computeroutput>" as the domain name. 
      These parameters must match
      those you set up in the qmail control files. In particular, the
      domain names must match, and the <emphasis>short name</emphasis> must match the
      second string you entered in the <filename>virtualdomains</filename> 
      file. In this case, we entered 
      "<computeroutput>here.there.com:webmail-there</computeroutput>",
      so we choose "<emphasis>there</emphasis>" as the short name.</para>

    <para>You then have to add a user to the domain and give that person
      an email address. While you're at it, create an email account for the admin 
      of this domain, and click the <emphasis>choose admin</emphasis> link 
      to assign that person as the admin for the domain.  This person will receive
      any undeliverable mail in a reserved mailbox called 
      <computeroutput>SYSTEM</computeroutput>.  If you do not assign an admin,
      bounced mail will cause a parse error and remain in the queue directory. </para>
      

    <para>To test the system, go to the <ulink url="/webmail">webmail</ulink> user pages 
    as the user whose account you created, and send an email to yourself.  Wait a minute
    and then click <emphasis>check mail</emphasis> to see if it has arrived.  If that 
    works, try sending and receiving from an external address.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-appendix-a-troubleshooting" xreflabel="Appendix A: Troubleshooting">
    <title>Appendix A: Troubleshooting</title>

    <para><phrase>Mail is not getting delivered.</phrase></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>First check that qmail is delivering mail properly to your
	  queue. You may do this by viewing the qmail log at
	  <filename>/var/log/syslog/</filename> to see what qmail is doing with the
	  mail. If there are no errors there, use root access to view the
	  contents of the queue: 

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# ls /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/new
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If you don't see any messages (and qmail says it 
	  delivered them succesfully to your webmail address), qmail is not 
	  delivering mail to the right queue. Manually check the alias files 
	  in the qmail directory: 

	  <programlisting>
$ su
# ls -a /home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias
.qmail-there-foo  (this is user foo's alias)
# cat .qmail-there-foo
/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/
	  </programlisting>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If this does not point to the right qmail queue directory, you
	  have not correctly configured the QueueDirectory parameter in
	  Webmail. Change the QueueDirectory parameter to point to
	  <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/</filename>,
	  delete the user "foo" and then recreate his account. If the file
	  .qmail-there-foo is not there, you need to set the AliasDirectory
	  parameter to point to
	  <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias/</filename>
	  and delete and recreate the user.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>If mail is showing up in the correct queue directory, try
	  processing the queue manually:

	  <programlisting>
SQL&gt; execute wm_process_queue('/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/new');
	  </programlisting>

	  If the command fails and the error message says something like
	  "file permission not granted", then go check
	  <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail</filename> and
	  <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/new</filename>. Make sure both
	  of them have "oracle" as the owner. Another possible reason is that
	  Oracle database user used by AOLServer has not been granted java
	  execution privilege. Grant it the appropriate pemission, that
	  should fix the problem.</para>

	<simpara>You may also check that messages were actually inserted into
	  Oracle by looking at the <computeroutput>wm_messages</computeroutput> table. It is
	  possible that these messages were inserted but not mapped to the
	  user, in which case, they will show up in the admin's SYSTEM mailbox. The main
	  reason for this happening is if the <emphasis>short name</emphasis> which you set
	  up in the admin page does not match the entry in
	  <filename>/var/qmail/control/virtualdomains</filename>. Fix this and then
	  try resending mail.</simpara>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-appendix-b-notes-for-webmail" xreflabel="Appendix B: Notes for WebMail">
    <title>Appendix B: Notes for WebMail</title>

    <para>Once the domain has been set up, you can start adding email
      accounts. An email account is tied to an ACS user; Email accounts
      can be assigned to users by using the administration pages.</para>

    <para>When an email account is added, a file is created automatically
      in the alias directory of the form "<filename>.qmail-[short domain
      name]-username</filename>" (e.g., "<filename>.qmail-wm-jsc</filename>") 
      that contains one line with the full path to the queue directory
      (<filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/</filename>). This file
      specifies that mail sent to "<computeroutput>webmail-there-foo@here.there.com</computeroutput>" be
      delivered to the maildir directory that we have set up. All email
      to be handled by the webmail system ends up in the same place
      (<filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/queue/new</filename>). The
      system uses the RFC822 Delivered-To header to distinguish who it
      should be displayed to. The redirection through the .qmail alias
      files is done so that only email sent to valid accounts will be
      received. Email sent to an address that does not have a .qmail file
      set up for it will bounce normally.</para>

    <para>Once every minute, Oracle polls the new directory of the maildir
      queue and picks up any mail that has been delivered. Using the
      JavaMail library running inside Oracle, it stores and parses the
      message, and saves off various pieces of information (parsed
      headers, attachments, etc.; see the data model).</para>

    <para><phrase>Migration Issues</phrase></para>

    <para>I have not written a complete migration script for updating
      old Webmail installations to the new data model.  There are a few
      useful functions included in the file <computeroutput>
      /webmail/scripts/webmail-migrate.sql</computeroutput>.  Feel free
      to contact <ulink url="mailto:erik@arsdigita.com">Erik Bielefeldt</ulink>
       if you need advice regarding migration.
    </para>

    <para><phrase>Performance Issues</phrase></para>

    <para>The original Webmail was a little bit infamous for being a slug
      when many users were on at once. Whether or not it deserved that
      reputation, I have sought to improve the data model, simplify
      overly complex queries, and tune things to run reasonably well (see
      the <xref linkend="design"></xref> for details). 
    </para>
    
    <para>Here are the results of my load testing:</para>

    <para><phrase>environment:</phrase></para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Sparc Ultra 10 333MHz processor</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>1 GB RAM</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Oracle 8.1.7</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>20,000 rows in the users table</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>80,000 mailboxes</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>137,000 messages</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>1,455,000 headers</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>1,900 attachments</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><phrase>results:</phrase></para> 

    <para>I did not test the search functions, as the efficiency of the query
      varies highly upon the particular user's search.  The following results 
      are biased towards heavy use of the <computeroutput>index</computeroutput>
      and <computeroutput>message</computeroutput> pages, 
      with some <computeroutput>folder-index</computeroutput>,
      <computeroutput>preferences</computeroutput>, 
      <computeroutput>index-view</computeroutput>, 
      and <computeroutput>index-search</computeroutput>
      pages thrown in.  I tested the sending of messages seperately, but obtained
      similar performance to the following results.
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Capable of sustaining 3 hits/sec. up to 100 concurrent requests</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Longest query takes .4 seconds.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Transfer rates of 30 Kb/s (I.e. 30Kb of data served per second by Webmail)</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>
        I was a little disappointed by these results, but after 
	spending several
	days tuning this was the best that I could come up with.
	As I expected, the index view was the costliest to produce,
	and even with caching of the message ids it was quite slow.
	However, I do not know of a reasonable way to speed it up.
      </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="install-appendix-c-customizing-the-qmail-configuration" xreflabel="Appendix C: Customizing the qmail configuration">
    <title>Appendix C: Customizing the qmail configuration</title>

    <para>It is possible to choose different alias and queue directories
      in the qmail setup. To choose a different alias directory, simply
      follow the installation instructions above, but substitute the
      desired directory for
      <filename>/home/aol32/servers/<replaceable>yourservername</replaceable>/qmail/alias</filename>.
      The queue directory may also be moved freely. Remember to update
      the AliasDirectory and QueueDirectory parameters.</para>

    <para>Webmail has been successfully used on a server cluster
      (<emphasis>iluvcamp</emphasis> has used 6 servers for over 100,000 
      users). A couple things to note: 
      You should choose one server to handle all incoming mail and 
      the processing of the queue by Oracle (presumably the machine the 
      database is running on).
      All of your AolServer instances may serve Webmail pages, however,
      you must place the alias directory in a 
      directory which is commonly accessible by all your servers. 
      Generally, this will not be under 
      <filename>/home/aol32</filename>.  A good bet would be under
      your <filename>/web/servername/</filename> directory.
      If you fail to do this, each server will end up having a different 
      set of aliases on it (and your mail will start bouncing).  
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>



<!--
 Local Variables:
 sgml-parent-document: ("index.xml" "chapter" "sect1")
 End:
-->
