<sect1 id="requirements" xreflabel="Webmail Application Requirements">
  <title>Webmail Application Requirements</title>

  <para>
    by <ulink url="mailto:erik@arsdigita.com">Erik Bielefeldt</ulink> 
  </para>

  <sect2 id="requirements-introduction" xreflabel="Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>This document describes the requirements for the ACS Webmail
      application. The Webmail application provides a web-based email
      service.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-vision-statement" xreflabel="Vision Statement">
    <title>Vision Statement</title>

    <para>Web-based email is a convenient and highly accessible way of
      communicating over the internet. Because web-based email only
      requires a browser, it is accessible from almost any connected
      computer, and because all the messages are stored on a server, it
      is easy for the user to check his or her mail from a number of
      different machines. The Webmail application aims to achieve the
      following goals:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Provide a reliable web-based email service</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Provide a simple, but powerful 
	  user-interface</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Provide a service competitive with other commercial web-based
	  email services</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Provide a scalable data-model and efficient 
	  implementation</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Integerate seemlessly with the ACS core (and other
	  modules)</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis>See <xref linkend="requirements-competitive-analysis"></xref>
	for further discussion of what Webmail should and should not provide 
	in the future.</emphasis>
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-systemapplication-overview" xreflabel="System/Application Overview">
    <title>System/Application Overview</title>

    <para>The Webmail application consists of:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>An interface for the user including: 

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Browsing available messages</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Reading specific messages</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Composing outgoing messages</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Customizing the user interface and functionality of the
		application</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>An interface for the administrator which includes: 

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para>Creating and deleting domains handled by Webmail</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Adding and deleting users in those domains</para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para>Viewing a list of recent Webmail errors</para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-use-cases-and-user-scenarios" xreflabel="Use-cases and User-scenarios">
    <title>Use-cases and User-scenarios</title>

    <para>The Webmail application is intended to provide ArsDigita
      employees and community members a web-based email service. Users
      would be community members who are looking for a convenient
      mail-service which would seamlessly integrate with other ACS tools,
      or people looking to escape highly commercialized mail-systems like
      Hotmail or Yahoo! Mail.</para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-competitive-analysis" xreflabel="Competitive Analysis">
    <title>Competitive Analysis</title>

    <para>As a pure web-based email system, Webmail will equal, and
      eventually surpass Hotmail, Yahoo! Mail, and other commercial
      web-based email services in usability and functionality.</para>

    <para>In comparison to other mail solutions as a whole (this includes
      IMAP, POP, and custom solutions), however, there is still a lot
      lacking. The user-interfaces of web-based email systems tend to be
      somewhat more cumbersome than specialized mail clients like
      Microsoft Outlook and Netscape Messenger. Their strength is their
      accessibility--all that is needed is a web browser. The optimal
      solution for an individual, however, might a combination of both: a
      specialized client which can be run on the user's primary machine
      and web-based access for those times when that individual does not
      have access to the primary machine. There are already systems which
      allow this, including several free IMAP versions. The advantage of
      IMAP systems is that they are based on a standard protocol which
      allows users to choose their client application. They also allow
      users to store messages on the server rather than on the client,
      thus allowing the messages to be accesible from numerous
      locations.</para>

    <para>The question facing ArsDigita is what sort of a solution would
      we like to be able to provide? Webmail certainly offers basic email
      functionality to any site which chooses to install it, and this is
      probably enough for most casual users, but it does not offer a
      complete solution for a business looking to provide their employees
      or customers with a high-powered email system for business use.
      There are several options ArsDigita can take in continuing webmail
      development: (arranged from easiest to most difficult to
      implement)</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>Continue improvements on the current system--keeping it
	  web-based but trying to offer the most powerful, flexible features
	  of any web-based system. For anyone who moves around a lot,
	  Web-based solutions are the most accessible. With continued
	  improvement, the user interface could be made to match that of
	  client-based solutions.</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Integrate the ACS with an existing IMAP solution, relying on
	  their product for functionality (with some customizations), but
	  providing a seemless user-experience and crossover between their
	  system and other ACS functionalities</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Develop a custom server (probably IMAP) for ACS</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist><para>

      Email is such a core part of building a community that I believe
      that ArsDigita must provide some form of it. Whether it is worth
      the resources to provide something beyond the current web-based
      system still needs to be assessed.
    </para></sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-related-links" xreflabel="Related Links">
    <title>Related Links</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><xref linkend="design"></xref></para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><xref linkend="install"></xref></para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements--requirements-data-model" xreflabel="Requirements: Data Model">
    <title>Requirements: Data Model</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><phrase>10.0 Domains</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>10.1</phrase> Domains have a full domain name</para>
	  <para><phrase>10.2</phrase> Domains have a short name for internal use</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>20.0 Users</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>20.1</phrase> Users have an email user name</para>
	  <para><phrase>20.2</phrase> Users are associated with a domain</para>
	  <para><phrase>20.3</phrase> Users have a referenced column in the users table</para>
	</listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>30.0 Mailboxes</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>30.1</phrase> Mailboxes are associated with users</para>
	  <para><phrase>30.2</phrase> Mailboxes are uniquely identified by name and
	  associated user</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>40.0 Incoming Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>40.1</phrase> Messages are associated with mailboxes (and hence to
	  users)</para>
	  <para><phrase>40.2</phrase> Messages have various flags to record their states
	  (deleted, answered, read, draft, etc.)</para>
	  <para><phrase>40.3</phrase> Messages have headers associated with them which keep
	  track of their header information</para>
	  <para><phrase>40.4</phrase> Messages have attachments associated with them which
	  store any data received as an attachment</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>50.0 Outgoing Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>50.1</phrase> Messages are associated with the composing user</para>
	  <para><phrase>50.2</phrase> Messages have headers associated with them which keep
	  track of their header information</para>
	  <para><phrase>50.3</phrase> Messages have attachments associated with them which
	  store any data received as an attachment</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements--requirements-webmail-administration" xreflabel="Requirements: Webmail Administration">
    <title>Requirements: Webmail Administration</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><phrase>60. 0 Creating Domains</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>60.1</phrase> The administrator may create or delete domains for
	  which Webmail will accept mail
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>70.0 Creating Webmail Accounts</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>70.1</phrase> The administrator may create or delete user Webmail
	  accounts</para>
	  <para><phrase>70.2</phrase> The administrator may set the size limit(in mb) of
	  Webmail accounts
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements--requirements-webmail-user-interface" xreflabel="Requirements: Webmail User Interface">
    <title>Requirements: Webmail User Interface</title>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><phrase>80.0 Browsing Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>80.1</phrase> The user may browse any of his or her existing
	  mailboxes</para>
	  <para><phrase>80.2</phrase> Messages are listed by address, subject, size, whether
	  it has been read, and time</para>
	  <para><phrase>80.3</phrase> The user may sort the messages by any of the above
	  columns
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>90.0 Reading Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>90.1</phrase> The user can view the body and certain headers of the
	  message</para>
	  <para><phrase>90.2</phrase> The user can move, delete, forward, or reply to the
	  message</para>
	  <para><phrase>90.3</phrase> The user may skip to the next, next unread, previous,
	  and previous unread messages, or to the browsing view (index)
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>100.0 Composing Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>100.1</phrase> The user may enter the following fields: recipient,
	  cc, bcc, subject, body</para>
	  <para><phrase>100.2</phrase> Only the recipient is required</para>
	  <para><phrase>100.3</phrase> The user may upload and attach files to the
	  message</para>
	  <para><phrase>100.4</phrase> The user may attach a signature</para>
	  <para><phrase>100.5</phrase> The user may select whether to allow html tags in the
	  message</para>
	  <para><phrase>100.6</phrase> The user may view an html preview of their
	  message
	</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>110.0 Filtering Messages</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>110.1</phrase> The user may filter messages by any message header,
	  body, status, mailbox, and age</para>
	  <para><phrase>110.2</phrase> Filters can be applied to incoming messages and have
	  an associated action executed upon that message</para>

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para><phrase>110.2.1</phrase> Actions include refiling, deleting, and
		forwarding
	      </para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>

	  <para><phrase>110.3</phrase> Filters can be used to generate views based on the
	  filter constraints</para>
	  

	  <itemizedlist>
	    <listitem><para><phrase>110.3.1</phrase> Views can be saved, edited, and applied
	      </para></listitem>

	    <listitem><para><phrase>110.3.2</phrase> Views can be created on the fly as dynamic
		searches
	      </para></listitem>
	  </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>

      <listitem><para><phrase>120.0 Security</phrase></para>
	  <para><phrase>120.1</phrase> The user may only access messages in his or her own
	  mailboxes -- this includes reading, browsing, responding to, and
	  forwarding</para>
	  <para><phrase>120.2</phrase> The user may only modify or delete folders that he or
	  she created</para>
	  <para><phrase>120.3</phrase> The user may only modify or delete filters that he or
	  she created</para>
	  <para><phrase>120.4</phrase> The user's mail is not visible to any other user,
	  including all admins
	</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id="requirements-revision-history" xreflabel="Revision History">
    <title>Revision History</title>

    <informaltable><tgroup cols="4">
	<thead>
	  <row>
	    <entry align="center">Document Revision #</entry>
	    <entry align="center">Action Taken, Notes</entry>
	    <entry align="center">When?</entry>
	    <entry align="center">By Whom?</entry>
	  </row>
	</thead>

	<tbody>
	  <row>
	    <entry>0.1</entry>
	    <entry>Creation</entry>
	    <entry>09/04/2000</entry>
	    <entry>Erik Bielefeldt</entry>
	  </row>

	  <row>
	    <entry>0.2</entry>
	    <entry>Fixed a few errors and added new features</entry>
	    <entry>11/10/2000</entry>
	    <entry>Erik Bielefeldt</entry>
	  </row>
	</tbody></tgroup></informaltable>

    <para><ulink url="mailto:erik@arsdigita.com">erik@arsdigita.com</ulink></para>
    <para>
      Last modified: $Date$
    </para>
  </sect2>
</sect1>



<!--
 Local Variables:
 sgml-parent-document: ("index.xml" "chapter" "sect1")
 End:
-->
